<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor of the city of London and the court of Aldermen at Bow-Church, on the feast of S. Michael, 1682 : the day for election of a Lord Mayor / by Henry Dove ...</title>
            <author>Dove, Henry, 1640-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11946527</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11946527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1003:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor of the city of London and the court of Aldermen at Bow-Church, on the feast of S. Michael, 1682 : the day for election of a Lord Mayor / by Henry Dove ...</title>
                  <author>Dove, Henry, 1640-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXII [1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 31.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51325:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right Honorable The Lord Mayor Of the CITY of <hi>LONDON,</hi> AND THE Court of ALDERMEN.</p>
            <p>At <hi>BOW-CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> on the FEAST of S. MICHAEL, 1682.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Day for the Election of a</hi> Lord Mayor.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY DOVE,</hi> D. D. One of His Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke,</hi> at the Ship in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51325:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51325:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Sir <hi>JOHN MOORE,</hi> Kt. Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London;</hi> And to the COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY deſign in Preaching this Sermon was to recommend the Duty of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and leſt I ſhould confute it firſt my ſelf, it is now Printed. I could ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily have declined both with the ordinary excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, The difficulty of the task and of the times, The cenſoriouſneſs of the Age, or my own unfitneſs, and might ſlily ſeek applauſe by framing an Apology: But as Obedience makes no delays, ſo it admits of no Excuſes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:51325:3"/> where the Authority is good, and the thing not unreaſonable: And therefore, ſuch as it is, I have expoſed it to Publick View un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Patronage, hoping it may in ſome meaſure edifie the Readers as it pleaſed the Hearers.</p>
            <p>And I am bold to prefix your Lordſhips Name to it, becauſe you countenance the Doctrine by your Example, being Eminent in thoſe Virtues which commend a Pious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Magiſtrate and a Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. That the King may never want ſuch Faithful Subjects, nor this Famous City ſuch Magiſtrates, as are true to the real Intereſt of the People by their Immovable Fidelity to the Crown, and Conformity to the Eſtabliſhed Laws, is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obedient Servant, HEN. DOVE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51325:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>TITUS III. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates.—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>VVHen S. <hi>Paul</hi> had converted the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians to the Faith of Chriſt, and was conſtrained to leave the Iſland that he might Preach the Goſpel to other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; he left <hi>Titus</hi> behind him with full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to <hi>ſet</hi> ſuch <hi>things in order</hi> as his ſhort ſtay there would not allow him to reform, and to <hi>ordain Presbyters in every City,</hi> that ſo the whole Iſland might be furniſhed with able Paſtors, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
            <p>And to the end, both <hi>He</hi> and <hi>They</hi> might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duty to the benefit of the Church, he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51325:4"/> gives him inſtructions in this Epiſtle how he ſhould govern himſelf and thoſe committed to his charge: what Doctrine he ſhould Preach, and what Diſcipline he ſhould uſe throughout his <hi>Province;</hi> and that not only with an eye to the general duties of the Goſpel, which are here compendiouſly laid down for all orders and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of men; but with a ſpecial regard to thoſe errors and vices, which the Apoſtle had obſerv'd moſt riſe among 'em.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are many</hi> (ſays he) <hi>unruly and vain talkers and deceivers, who ſubvert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucres ſake: And their mouths muſt be ſtopt;</hi> chap. 1. 10. There are others notorious for Lying, Luxury and Sloth; for which they are branded by one of their own Poets; and I am alſo able to atteſt the ſame from the little experience I had of 'em: <hi>This wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is true; wherefore rebuke them ſharply, that they may be ſound in the Faith,</hi> ver. 13. There are ſome that give heed to <hi>Jewiſh Fables,</hi> and Phariſaical Traditions, teaching the commandments of men for the doctrines of God, and ſo <hi>turning</hi> themſelves and others <hi>from</hi> the <hi>Truth, ver.</hi> 14. men of defiled minds and conſciences, Chriſtians in name, but Heathens in manners, filling up their iniquity with the leven of Hypocriſie, <hi>For they profeſs indeed that they know God, but in works
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51325:4"/> they deny him,</hi> ver. 16. There are others given to brawling, contention, and evil ſpeaking, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 2. and they were probably ſuch as were taxed before for idleneſs, ſuch as ſpent their time like the men of <hi>Athens</hi> in hearing or talking of ſome new matter; idle in their own, and buſie in other mens affairs, doing any thing but what they ſhould, or nothing to the purpoſe, or that which is worſe than nothing: For idleneſs we know is the teeming mother of Vice and Miſchief, and was indeed the epidemical ſin of that people; and therefore he charges 'em again and again, that they take upon themſelves ſome honeſt profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and abide in the ſtation allotted to them, and perform the duties of their own calling; which is the importance of thoſe phraſes, <hi>Be careful to maintain good works,</hi> ver. 8. and <hi>let ours learn to maintain good works for neceſſary uſes,</hi> ver. 14. This is the way to preſerve Unity in the Church, and Peace in the State; and 'twill diſpoſe 'em in time to maintain the works of their heavenly calling too: For when men keep to their own ſtation, and do the works of their proper calling, they are in God's way, and have the promiſe of his bleſſing; But when they are idle, they lie open to all the wiles of Satan; and hence they are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contentious, turbulent and miſchievous: when they will needs be medling where they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51325:5"/> to do, and thruſting an Oar into every Boat, when they leave their own ſtation, and invade an other mans office, there is confuſion and every evil work; there is railing and reviling, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and back-biting, rancor and ſpite; there the heart is fill'd with malice, and the tongue with deadly poiſon, and the hand with violence or blood.</p>
            <p>And to name no more, for the Country was full of the like diſorders; there were others ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Faction and Sedition, eſpecially thoſe of the Jewiſh party; repining at the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under which they liv'd, and ready upon every occaſion to ſtir and foment tumults: For of all the Nations under heaven the Jews were moſt impatient of a Forein Yoke, and having been once Gods peculiar people under his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate government and care, (though by the juſt judgment of God upon 'em they had now forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that high Prerogative) they could not endure to think of ſubmitting themſelves to Strangers, nor brook ſubjection unto Heathen Governors. Nay, there was one Sect among 'em infatuated with the error of <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee, Acts 5. 37. who in the days of taxing had drawn away much people</hi> under this pretence, that the <hi>children of Abraham</hi> ought not to be ſubject to the <hi>Pagan Emperors,</hi> becauſe they were aliens from the <hi>loins of Abraham,</hi> and the <hi>Commonwealth of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51325:5"/>
            <p>Theſe were ſcatter'd up and down in moſt quarters of the Empire, and doubtleſs they ſwarm'd in that rich and populous Iſland, renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for no leſs than an <hi>hundred Cities,</hi> ſince they were likely to gain moſt Proſelytes and Abettors in ſuch places. Hence S. <hi>Hierom</hi> tells us, that the reaſon why the Apoſtle ſo often inculcates the doctrine of ſubjection and obedience, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly here in the Text, was to cure the ſcandal which the ſeditious practices of theſe men had brought upon other Chriſtians, who were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally traduc'd as evil doers, and ſometimes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd Perſecution upon this ſcore, and to vindicate the honor of Chriſtianity it ſelf, which was blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed among the Gentiles for their ſakes.</p>
            <p>This was the ſtate of the Cretians in thoſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly days of the Goſpel, when S. <hi>Paul</hi> commanded <hi>Titus</hi> to <hi>teach and exhort, and rebuke 'em with all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;</hi> And if there be any in theſe laſt and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous times, to whom their character, either in part or in the whole is ſuited, ſure we have ſo much the more reaſon now, to <hi>warn the unruly</hi> and to animate the good Subject, by how much the Government under which we live, (bleſſed be God for it) is incomparably more eaſie, juſt and good, than that of the firſt Ages. And therefore I beſeech you to hearken with meekneſs, while I <hi>ſpeak the words that become ſound doctrine,</hi> not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51325:6"/> or accuſe any, unleſs their own hearts condemn 'em, but to ſhew the reaſonableneſs and equity of our dutiful Obedience to the <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Government.</hi> And for ſo doing, not only the Doctrine it ſelf, but the diſcretion of the choice, is ſufficiently warranted from this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Commiſſion. <hi>Put them in mind to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words we may obſerve three general parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Publick Authority preſuppos'd. <hi>Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. Subjection and obedience enjoyn'd. <hi>To be ſubject and to obey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. The duty of Miniſters inculcated. <hi>Put them in mind.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of theſe briefly in their order as they plainly lie before us: To which I ſhall add ſuch reaſons and motives as may endear the duty to us; and then conclude with a word in ſeaſon, to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that brought us hither.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Publick Authority preſuppos'd under the words [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] Principalities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: For <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are not expreſſed in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, but ſeem to be added in our Tranſlation to explain the other, as by an uſual Figure in Holy Writ. The Power it ſelf is put for the Perſons endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it; the abſtract for the concrete, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 11.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51325:6"/> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 38. And to ſave me the labour of Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, it is twice together in one Verſe, <hi>Rom. 13. 3. For Rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil; wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power? do that which is good.</hi> Where <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> interpret each other; and by good and evil works is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant, the <hi>doers of ſuch works.</hi> To be ſubject therefore to the Power, is to ſubmit to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons inveſted with it; as S. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo enjoyns in that known place, 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 13. Submit your ſelves unto every ordinance of man for the Lord's ſake;</hi> to every humane creature, ſo 'tis literally tranſlated, though our Mother Tongue does ſcarce reach the importance of it: For 'tis an Idiom originally deriv'd from the Hebrew Language, wherein <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or creature is often put for Man, becauſe he is the moſt excellent of all the viſible Creation, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 15. And hence the Syriac renders it, To all the ſons of men, that have the preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence among you; to all that excel in Dignity and Authority, Subordinate or Supreme: For ſo, to put all out of doubt, the Apoſtle interprets himſelf, ver. 14. <hi>Whether it be to the King as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, or unto Governors, as unto them that are ſent by him for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi> And this I note by the way, becauſe the Papiſts on one hand, and the Sectaries on the other have made ſuch a ſtir about
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51325:7"/> this phraſe, and are glad of any appearance from Holy Writ, that they may leſſen or invalidate the Authority of Kings, while one ſide would have 'em derive it from the <hi>Pope,</hi> the other from the <hi>People;</hi> and tho they manage the Argument by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>mediums,</hi> yet they both agree in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is to bring 'em under, or to pull 'em down, as it beſt ſerves their turn. For tho it be ſtiled here, <hi>an Ordinance of man,</hi> becauſe it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd among men, and chiefly reſpects them, yet by S. <hi>Paul</hi> it is expreſly called, <hi>The Ordinance of God,</hi> becauſe it is deriv'd from him alone. <hi>Rom. 13. 2. Whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> And here again our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the King is required for the Lord's ſake; and why for his? but becauſe the Lord hath ordain'd him as his Vicegerent upon Earth for the adminiſtration of Publick Juſtice, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing Rewards and Puniſhments according to mens deſerts. And becauſe he is <hi>God's Creature,</hi> not only as he is a man, but as he is a Magiſtrate, <hi>Be obedient to him in well doing; for ſo is the will of God, that with well doing ye may put to ſilence the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of fooliſh men,</hi> ver. 15. That you may ſtop the mouths of the Heathens, who will judg of your Religion by your actions, and think that no better than your ſelves; for if you diſturb the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51325:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> peace of the world, reaſon it ſelf will bid 'em conclude, Surely that Religion is not from God, which teaches men to break the Civil Peace, and perverts the ends of Government. There is no way to anſwer the Argument, or avoid the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, but by your dutiful Obedience, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſubmit your ſelves; for ſo is the will of God: were it not his Ordinance, he would never will it. Which brings me to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Subjection and Obedience enjoyn'd, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The firſt imports Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Subordination in a regular way, where ſome are above, and others gradually below: The ſecond denotes properly Obedience to the juſt Laws and Commands, by which I mean ſuch, as do not interfere with Gods. For in every pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and great Community, there is of neceſſity a Supreme Power, whether it be lodged in few or more: and in every Kingdom where the Crown is Imperial, a Supreme Governor next under God, to whom all the reſt are ſubject by Gods appointment. There is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> on Gods part, and an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> on ours; the Ordinance and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is Gods, the Submiſſion and Obedience ours, according to the will of God. And the Rule of our Obedience is as plain as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is poſitive, whether we reſpect <hi>Liberty,</hi> or <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or both together, which are the uſual
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51325:8"/> pleas againſt it: If that paſs into a Law, which is not repugnant or inconſiſtent with the Laws of God, we muſt needs obey it; if it be repugnant we muſt needs ſubmit under it, tho we muſt not comply with it; for here that antecedent Rule takes place, <hi>To obey God rather than man.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which is unalterable and eternal, becauſe God is higher than the higheſt, the Almighty So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign and Law-giver. And this is implyed in the words immediately following the Text, leſt men ſhould think the Apoſtle requires it right or wrong, <hi>Put them in mind to obey Magiſtrates, to be ready to every good work:</hi> intimating to us, that we muſt ſhew our Obedience by our ready comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in good works; for if the Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what is evil, there is no obligation to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, becauſe nothing can oblige us to do evil. But what if the thing commanded be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor evil, but of an indifferent nature; what muſt we do in that caſe? why then we muſt undoubtedly obey it; for otherwiſe there will be nothing left wherein the Magiſtrate may uſe his Power: What is good or evil in it ſelf, muſt be done or avoided <hi>for Gods ſake:</hi> what is not ſo in it ſelf, but only in regard of the end for which it is enacted, being judg'd ſo by the Magiſtrate for the good of the Community; this muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, both for <hi>God's ſake,</hi> and <hi>his too,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51325:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> God requires our Obedience to him in theſe things. But what then becomes of our <hi>Liberty,</hi> if another muſt judg for us? It is where it was before; we muſt obey, and yet we are as <hi>Free</hi> as Chriſt hath made us; nay, I doubt not to add, we are moſt <hi>Chriſt's Freemen,</hi> when we duly obey our Governors juſt Laws; for ſeeing Chriſt hath commanded us to be ſubject not only for <hi>wrath,</hi> but for <hi>conſcience</hi> ſake, that ſo we may avoid the guilt of ſin, that Obedience which keeps us from ſin, (which is the only vaſſallage of a Chriſtian) can by no means infringe, but does rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance our <hi>Chriſtian liberty. As free</hi> (ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 16. and not uſing your liberty for a cloak of maliciouſneſs, but as the ſervants of God.</hi> As though he had ſaid, Don't urge your <hi>liberty</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a pretence to cover your <hi>craftineſs;</hi> as if that would excuſe your Diſobedience; you are free indeed from ſin, but not from your Obedience; Servants of God and yet Subjects to your Prince; and ſo much the better Servants, by how much the more you are good Subjects.</p>
            <p>Another pretence of near a kin to the former is that of <hi>Private Conſcience;</hi> for here again 'tis plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if I judg the thing commanded to be evil, I cannot be free from ſin; for to me at leaſt it is ſin if I comply with the command during that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, becauſe the Apoſtle aſſures me, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51325:9"/> is not of Faith is ſin.</hi> But what if that perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be falſe and erroneous, doſt thou not in cur a greater ſin? What if it be not aſſuredly grounded on the clear word of God, but only in thine own Opinion? muſt a private Opinion weigh down the ballance againſt the publick good, the laws of the Community, the conſcience of thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, and the great Rule of Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the Word of God? That Word commands thee to Obey, and ſo binds thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; thy Conſcience bids thee not, and ſo binds thee; which of theſe in reaſon ſhall take place? muſt the Word be null'd by the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or the Conſcience guided by the Word? What a ſad condition is that man in, who brings himſelf into theſe ſtraits, where Conſcience which ſhould be his guide becomes his greateſt ſnare? For ſuch is the nature of an <hi>erroneous Conſcience,</hi> that it unavoidably betrays a man to ſin, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he follows it, or whether he reſiſts it; if he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows his Conſcience, he ſins, becauſe it is errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; if he reſiſts it, though it be erroneous, he ſins againſt his Conſcience. What then ſhall be done, or which way ſhall he turn him in theſe perplexities? Why, I know no expedient but one, that he ſpeedily burſt his ſhackles which himſelf has faſtned and not God, by ridding himſelf of ſuch a Conſcience. And the way to do it is this;</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51325:9"/>
            <p>That he be not overwiſe in his own conceit, nor lean too much to his own underſtanding, but allow the poſſibility at leaſt of his being in an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear, that he is but a man, and not infallible: That he lay by Paſſion and Prejudice, Partiality and Intereſt, and ſincerely examine the grounds of his perſuaſion, <hi>not as pleaſing men, but God, who tryeth our hearts:</hi> That he humbly conſult better judgments, whoſe Office it is to inform and eaſe his Conſcience, namely his <hi>lawful Paſtors,</hi> whoſe lips preſerve knowledg, and are ſet over him in the Lord for that purpoſe: That he believe his Governors have a conſcience too, for which they muſt anſwer as well as himſelf; and ſeriouſly conſider whoſe plea is moſt likely to be admitted at Gods high Tribunal: And above all, that he earneſtly pray for the ſpirit of meekneſs and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, the ſpirit of wiſdom, diſcretion and holy fear, while he compares his Conſcience with the Rule of Gods Word impartially, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath promis'd that he will not deny his Spirit to ſuch an humble Petitioner and Enquirer.</p>
            <p>To theſe we may add in the laſt place the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>both together,</hi> I mean <hi>liberty of Conſcience.</hi> To which I ſhall only ſay two things, and I leave 'em to your ſober thoughts: Firſt, that Liberty of Conſcience, if it be well weigh'd, ſounds like a contradiction; for Liberty imports Freedom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51325:10"/> without reſtraint, but Conſcience was always bound ever ſince it was plac'd in humane ſouls; and though I am free indeed in regard of my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which proceed from my Conſcience, yet my Conſcience is not freed from the antecedent rule of my actions, which is the law of God; for by that it is always bound. The ſecond is this, There is no ſuch phraſe throughout the Bible as <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> not one place in Scripture where theſe words are joyn'd together, but for <hi>Obedience to our Governors</hi> there are twenty. I ſpeak to knowing men, judg ye, what I ſay.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Duty of Paſtors and Teachers incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Put 'em in mind, admoniſh 'em often of it, and bring it to their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: as S. <hi>Peter</hi> does twice together in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe, 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 12, 13. I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of theſe things, though ye know them, and be eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth. Yea, I think it meet, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to ſtir you up, by putting you in remembrance.</hi> There are ſome Duties we are apt to forget, or very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to remember; and ſome people there are who care not for a Preacher, that tells 'em often of their duty; inſomuch that a <hi>moral Preacher</hi> is made a by-word to fright the ignorant, and to render 'em averſe, ſince they know no better, to their <hi>Pariſh Guide.</hi> If he rub up their memories,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51325:10"/> and touch 'em in a ſore place, they have a preſent remedy for it, by hearing him no more, and think it ſufficient excuſe for their abſence or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſtray, to ſay, They do not like his way. But if a man ſet up a ſeparate Congregation in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Eſtabliſhed Laws and Worſhip, if he fill their heads with aiery Speculations inſtead of practical and ſearching Truths, if he daub with untemper'd mortar, or ſow pillows under their elbows, and can but help 'em to an evaſion from this Duty of Obedience, he ſhall have followers enough. This is a certain ſign, that tho men know their Duty, yet they do not love to hear it, ſince they forſake the Aſſemblies where they are honeſtly told of it. But (my Brethren) <hi>I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded better things of you, though I thus ſpeak, and things that accompany ſalvation:</hi> For certainly Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Magiſtrates is one of thoſe things, and if they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, then ſurely we may ſafely affirm, and that without any breach of Charity, or ſtretching beyond our line, That they who oppoſe 'em in lawful things, or refuſe to obey 'em in the ſame, without a timely Repentance and Reformation, are in great danger of it. Suffer me therefore, as the Apoſtles lead the way both by Precept and Example, to put you in remembrance of theſe things, though you know 'em as well as I, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51325:11"/> to inculcate a little further this Duty of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you cannot forget that you are Subjects, and you cannot but know that Subjects are bound in conſcience to obey their lawful Governors.</p>
            <p>Now that you may perform this Duty, not grudgingly or barely of neceſſity, but with chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and loyal hearts, let me commend theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing motives to your ſerious conſideration and conſcientious practice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider, That Obedience to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates is a prime Duty of Piety and Religion, wherein the Honor and Authority of God are particularly concerned; not only becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it by manifold Precepts, but becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are his Officers and Miniſters, by whom he governs the world, and adminiſters his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence towards men, and to whom he has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven part of his own Power for that purpoſe. He removeth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings, ſays <hi>Daniel,</hi> 2. 21. by him they reign, and by him they decree Juſtice, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 15. They are the Miniſters of God to us for good, ſays S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. 4. In his name and behalf they act, and him they repreſent, being God's viſible Deputies upon Earth by his own Commiſſion, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Power and Providence for our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: Hence he joyns 'em with himſelf, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtiles 'em by his own name, <hi>I have ſaid, ye
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51325:11"/> are Gods, Pſal. 82. 6. Jo.</hi> 10. 34. and frequently alſo by his Sons title, <hi>Mine Anointed. I have found</hi> David <hi>my Servant, with my Holy Oyl have I Anointed him.</hi> Pſal. 89. 20. An Emblem of their Sovereignty, and a Security alſo of their Perſons. And again, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed. Pſal.</hi> 105. 15. Which was a Prohibition given in Charge, before that Oyl was uſed, to render both, ſacred and inviolable. So that by obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Laws, and honouring their Perſons, we own the Authority of God, and ſubmit to it, but in the violation of either, God himſelf is ſlighted and affronted, and his Dominion in effect diſown'd. This was that which influenc'd <hi>David's</hi> heart, and tyed up his hands from offering Violence towards <hi>Saul;</hi> and tho' he was next Heir to the Crown, and already anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it; tho' <hi>Saul</hi> thirſted for his blood, and perſecuted him by force and fraud; tho' he had the hearts of the people, and <hi>Saul</hi> was given up into his hands, ſo that he could as eaſily have ſlain him, as he cut his skirt; I ſay, tho' he had all theſe plauſible incitements, and a whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination of pretences, yet this was that which kept him from ſo great Iniquity. [1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 6.] <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing unto my Maſter the Lords Anointed, to ſtretch forth my hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Lords Anointed.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51325:12"/> But here you'l ſay, Had <hi>Saul</hi> his Power from God? does God truſt his Authority in the hands of Evil Kings? So the Scripture tells us; For the Authority is ſtill from God, tho' it be placed in the hands of a ſinfull man, and it looſeth not its eſſence by the acceſſion of perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal miſcarriages: For theſe, he muſt ſtand or fall only to <hi>his own Maſter,</hi> and there is no Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal upon Earth can judge him. Hence <hi>Daniel</hi> acknowledges the Power of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to be given him of God. [<hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 37.] <hi>The God of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdom, Power and Strength, and Glory:</hi> Our Saviour own'd the Authority of <hi>Pilate,</hi> even when he Condemned him, to be from above, <hi>Joh. 19. 11. Thou couldſt have no Authority at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above.</hi> And <hi>Nero</hi> was Emperor when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and yet obſerve in that Chapter of Loyalty and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>Rom. 13. 1. The Powers</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that be</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that are now in being] <hi>are Ordained of God, ver.</hi> 4. and to him he Exhorts 'em to pay <hi>Tribute</hi> and <hi>Cuſtome, Fear</hi> and <hi>Honour, ver.</hi> 7. So that you ſee the ſins of the perſon doe not deſtroy the Power, but that it hath ſtill the ſame Original, For he that ordained <hi>David</hi> did alſo ſet up <hi>Saul, Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam, Ezekias</hi> and <hi>Ahab, Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Joſias, Nero</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51325:12"/> Julian</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> alternately good and bad; and he that hath ſaid in one place, <hi>By me Kings Reign,</hi> Prov. 8. 15. hath ſaid alſo in another, <hi>I gave 'em a King in mine Anger,</hi> Hoſea 13. 11. And from <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Job,</hi> we gather, That he maketh an Hypocrite to Reign, when he is minded to ſcourge a ſinful People. <hi>Job.</hi> 34. 30. The Authority therefore of both is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from God, To him <hi>alone</hi> they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and to him they muſt give an account, how they uſe or abuſe <hi>his Authority;</hi> But all the reſt are ſubject next under God to them, and muſt give an Account to both how they diſcharge this Duty of Obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The exigence of our Civil Affairs, and the Preſervation of the Publick does exact this Duty from us: For the Execution of Juſtice between man and man, the ſafe and quiet En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Gods Bleſſings, and the Welfare and Peace of the whole Community, are extreamly concern'd and advanced by it. Now as Peace, which is an ineſtimable good in it ſelf, and ſweetens all other Bleſſings, can never be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved without Government, ſo neither can Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſubſiſt without Obedience to it. If every man ſhould have his will, and do that which is right in his own Eyes, as they did when there was <hi>no King in</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Jud.</hi> 17. 6.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51325:13"/> there would be as many Wills and Affections as there are men: infinite competitions and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs quarrels would ariſe, for every man would ſtrive to draw all to his own Net, and Peace would be quite baniſh'd from the face of the Earth. No man could enjoy any thing quietly or ſafely but muſt deliver it up to a ſtronger than himſelf; he that can kill his Neighbor, will take his Poſſeſſions too, and the World would ſoon become <hi>a Den of Thieves.</hi> The only Remedy againſt this intolerable inconvenience is being determined by Laws under a common Judge and Arbitrator of differences, who is equally concern'd and indifferently affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, endued with Authority to decide emergent Caſes, and arm'd with force to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Violence and Rapine. To which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men ſhould, not only in duty and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but alſo in point of intereſt refer and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their pretences; and he that endeavours to enervate or defeat this excellent Proviſion for <hi>Publick Peace,</hi> may juſtly be reputed an Enemy to the whole Community, and ought to be puniſhed as a diſturber of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Obedience to our Governors is founded in the higheſt Equity and Reaſon: For day by day we receive invaluable benefits by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their Government and Conduct; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51325:13"/> of our Lives and Eſtates, of our Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Properties and Religion; ſecure Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Gifts of God, and Liberty to encreaſe our ſubſtance by Trade and Traffick, and to eat the fruit of our Labour, every man under his own Vine, while there is no breaking in, nor going out, no leading into Captivity, and no juſt complaining in our ſtreets. Happy are the People that are in ſuch a caſe, if we had but hearts to be thankful for it; and if we compare our condition with other Nations, we cannot but acknowledge our own happineſs: Yea, Bleſſed are we of this Iſland who enjoy theſe things in Peace, and may the Bleſſing of God reſt upon them who promote and preſerve our Peace. Wherefore let us unanimouſly ſhew forth our thankfulneſs by our Obedience, and chearfully endeavour in our ſeveral ſtations to uphold and maintain that Government that maintains and ſecures us: it is but an equal and juſt return, in regard of the benefits we receive from it; By that we enjoy <hi>great quietneſs</hi> and plenty; and therefore we ought to <hi>accept it always,</hi> and <hi>in all places, with all thankfulneſs.</hi> And if it be <hi>Equity</hi> to uphold the Government becauſe it upholds us, what is it but great <hi>Iniquity</hi> to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or diſturb that to which we ſtand ſo much indebted?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51325:14"/>4. Obedience to our Governours is a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on us in point of ingenuity and gratitude. For in preſerving the Peace and Proſperity of the Nation, they do not only preſerve ours, but for our advantage alſo they undergo many cares and troubles, great toyl and labour, <hi>attending continually for this very thing,</hi> Rom. 13. 6. It is a great miſtake in thoſe that judge only by appearances, to think the Lives of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours more pleaſant and eaſie than other mens; whereas indeed they are of all moſt difficult and full of Trouble. Their ſplendor and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendances, their Riches and affluence of outward things, and whatever elſe is neceſſary to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their State and Grandeur, does not half countervail their continual ſollicitudes and cares from within, their croſſes and diſappointments from without, the cenſures and obloquies of querulous and peeviſh perſons, the want of eaſe and liberty they ſuſtain, and all for our ſakes that we way live in quiet. In regard of what they do and endure for us, watching early and late for our good, they are deſervedly ſtiled <hi>Parents of their Countrey:</hi> and therefore 'tis an ungrateful thing to add to their burden, and increaſe their trouble by our frowardneſs and diſobedience; 'tis not only diſingenuous but unjuſt, not to render 'em freely what may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51325:14"/> encourage and comfort 'em in the diſcharge of their arduous Office, <hi>that they may do it with joy and not with grief.</hi> Obedience will make their Office eaſie, and our own condition ſafe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. No man can diſobey his Governours with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breaking the moſt Sacred Laws of Juſtice and Honeſty; without downright Perjury to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and perfidiouſneſs towards man. Every one as ſoon as he is born, is under the Protection of the Government, and becomes a Subject to his <hi>Natural Liege Lord;</hi> and therefore when he comes to exerciſe his ſenſes, and to diſcern between good and evil, as Religion and Reaſon will engage him to <hi>Fear God</hi> in the firſt place, who has given him Life and Being, ſo in the next, it will teach him, to <hi>Honour the King</hi> and ſubmit to the Government, by which under God he enjoys his Well-being; and he cannot but conceive himſelf under a natural ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of Obedience to the Laws of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, of which Providence and Nature have made him a Member. And in purſuance of this, as well as the Law of God, the Government has a Right to tye the Conſciences of men by the firmeſt bonds it can; and to exact <hi>Oaths of Allegiance,</hi> and Promiſes of Fidelity and Loyalty, that ſo it may ſecure and ſuſtain it ſelf, and be better enabled to Protect them. In which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51325:15"/> Promiſes and Oaths being once engag'd, it is horrible impiety and wickedneſs to violate 'em; for nothing can excuſe us from the obligation of an Oath, but the plain unlawfulneſs of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to which we are ſworn: Now this can never take place when we ſwear <hi>Allegiance</hi> only to our Lawful Governours, according to the will of God, the dictates of Nature, the reaſon of the thing, the Example of all Ages, and the known Laws of our own Nation. Wherefore <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings Commandment,</hi> and to live in Obedience to his Government, <hi>and that in regard of the Oath of God,</hi> 'Tis the Counſel of the Preacher <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8. 2. and 'tis my Duty to mind you of it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſeriouſly conſider'd, it will eaſily appear, That <hi>Diſobedience</hi> has all that is baſe in it, and that <hi>Rebellion</hi> contains a whole conjugation of Wickedneſs: of which there ſeems to be an undeniable ſenſe in all mens minds, ſince even they who love the thing, do uſually hate the name of Rebels, and ſuch as are conſcious of the guilt would gladly avoid the reproach of it; a plain indication of guilt, as guilt is a manifeſt Argument of Sin and Wickedneſs. And therefore it is well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> to Witchcraft, 1 <hi>Sam. 15. 23. Rebellion is as the Sin of Witchcraft,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51325:15"/> and ſtubborneſs is as Iniquity and Idolatry.</hi> 'Tis a Sin next to Blaſphemy to <hi>ſpeak evil of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> a degree of prophaneſs to diſobey 'em, and intolerable Iniquity to Rebell againſt 'em. It is as bad in its own nature as Murder or Theft, being as expreſly forbidden as theſe, and in its conſequence 'tis far more miſchievous: Witneſs the dreadful miſeries that uſherd in and enſued the diſſolution of a flouriſhing Monarchy within our own memories, when proſperous wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs prevail'd, and Rebellion rid in Triumph. For to rifle one man of his goods, is not ſo bad or hurtful, as to rob the Publick of its Peace; to ſet an Houſe on fire is not ſo peſtilent and hainous, as to be an Incendiary of the State, to make combuſtions in the Nation, and to blow up the Foundations of Publick Quiet: To poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or aſſaſſinate one private Perſon is not ſo horrid as to ſtabb a Common-wealth, to ſow the ſeed of Sedition in the Peoples minds, and to raiſe inteſtine commotions in it; in a word, to wrong one man is nothing in compariſon to the injuring of <hi>a Prince,</hi> and in <hi>Him</hi> the whole Common-weale; for in <hi>Him</hi> you wrong me and my Neighbour, and every one that is protected by <hi>Him,</hi> who are concerned in him, and ought to defend him as a <hi>Common Father.</hi> I might proceed to ſhew, how Rebellion debauches the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51325:16"/> 
               <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and hardens men in impiety, and opens a gap to all ſort of Villany; till at length they grow ſeared and ſenceleſs of the evil of Sin, and <hi>Conſcience</hi> leaves off to rebuke 'em for it: For when Subjects have drawn the Sword againſt their Sovereign, they uſually throw away the Scabbard, and 'tis rare very rare to find a <hi>Repenting Rebel.</hi> How 'tis directly oppoſite to <hi>the Spirit and Power of Chriſtianity,</hi> which is as its Author, holy and harmleſs, calm and gentle, meek and peaceable; and no leſs deſtructive to the practiſe of it, while it lets looſe the Reins, and opens the flood-gates of Ungodlineſs, gives vent to mens Paſſions, Luſts and Outrage, cancells all the endearments of Love and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and violates all Obligations Sacred and Civil: How it makes the very <hi>Profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> odious and deſpicable, and expoſeth it to contempt and reproach, as the great Cauſe of miſchief and diſturbance to the world; And this Experience hath ſadly ſhewn, for there is nothing hath prejudic'd and diſparag'd Religion among unconcern'd lookers on, more than the Factions and Seditions it hath cauſed; I mean the falſe pretences and ſhadow of Religion: for the Power of it hath no ſuch thing: <hi>Woe be to them by whom ſuch ſcandals come.</hi> And in brief, How 'tis contrary to the Example of Chriſt, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51325:16"/> Bleſſed Apoſtles, and the Primitive Saints and Chriſtians; who copyed out the precepts of the Goſpel by their practiſe, and did never oppoſe or diſturb the Government under which they liv'd. And if my time were not almoſt ſpent, I might alſo examine the pretences that have been made for <hi>Diſobedience</hi> and <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> and the evaſions men have found to elude (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) thoſe glorious patterns: For one has even libell'd the Primitive Chriſtians, aſcribing their meekneſs and ſubmiſſion to neceſſity, rather than their Religion or their Virtue, as though they wanted ſufficient Forces to reſiſt or perhaps Courage. [So <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>] Another ſticks not to ſay, that the Apoſtles themſelves in Preſcribing Subjection and Obedience, did it only to flatter the Emperours, and curry favour with them. [So <hi>Salmeron</hi>] A third has Taught, That the <hi>Doctrine of Reſiſtance</hi> was a Myſtery hid indeed from the firſt Ages, and reſerv'd for the laſt days of greater Light. [<hi>Jo. Goodwin,</hi> Anticav. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.] But what will not ſome men ſay, when they are put to a plunge, and pinch'd with the Evidence of a <hi>Plain Truth?</hi> The Bleſſed Apoſtles ſhall be called <hi>Paraſites</hi> and <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> rather than a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> will confeſs himſelf in the wrong; and the Goſpel it ſelf belied to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance that which it every where condemns.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51325:17"/>
            <p>But of all the Artifices which ſeditious ſpirits have taken up, there have been none more made uſe of, than the pretence of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Zeal,</hi> which hath been thought ſo creditable a Cauſe to engage in, that it could once convert the infamous title of <hi>Rebel</hi> or <hi>Traytor,</hi> to that of <hi>Patriot</hi> or <hi>Saint;</hi> and among thoſe that are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily blinded by their intereſt or ſucceſs, it hath quite ſmother'd the Odium of ſuch <hi>Engagements:</hi> Beſides which, it has had this advantage, That it always makes Conſcience of its Party, for fear it ſhould condemn it ſelf, and ſo ſtifles all doubts and ſcruples that might otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the undertaking: and as ſome men have told a lye ſo often till they believe it to be true, ſo have ſome <hi>biggoted zealots</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur'd their minds ſo much to Rebellious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that they think at laſt they are bound in Conſcience to put 'em in execution. We have had ſo many, and ſuch coſtly evidences of this, in this <hi>our Nation,</hi> that they tranſcend the moſt tragical deſcription. From hence have ſprung thoſe dangerous Poſitions whereby <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> hath been defended, and <hi>Rebellion</hi> openly maintain'd; hence thoſe pernicious maxims, at once deſtructive of Religion and Conſcience, of Laws and Government, <hi>That no Faith is to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>That Dominion is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51325:17"/> in Grace;</hi> I mention both together, not only becauſe they were both broached in the ſame School, but chiefly becauſe we of this Nation have ſmarted ſo deeply from both: The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> firſt ſet 'em on foot, and the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Fifth-Monarchiſts</hi> and other Sectaries followed their ſteps. And as 'tis the common Fate of Truth to ſuffer from both Extreams, while one ſide hath pleas'd to call us <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and the other to ſtile themſelves <hi>Saints,</hi> they have combin'd together, tho' they would never own the Confederacy, to diſturb an happy and well-ſetled Government, and to ruin (as much as in them lay) <hi>the beſt Conſtitution of Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the whole world.</hi> But (<hi>bleſſed be God, and again I ſay bleſſed</hi>) they are <hi>both</hi> ſtill in being; and they mutually ſtrengthen and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold each other: The <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi> of Chriſt is the Shield and Buckler of <hi>his Church</hi> amongſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by the Divine Protection of him we are alſo ſecured in the quiet enjoyment of our Lives and Fortunes, of our Laws and our Immunities, and in the free and open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Gods true Religion;</hi> Let us not forfeit ſo great bleſſings by our Ingratitude to God and the King, by our evil Lives and froward tempers, and diſobedience to thoſe Laws, which ſecure theſe things to us. We have an excellent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51325:18"/> 
               <hi>Government,</hi> to which Forreigners flee for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and ſtand in admiration at our happineſs; and they cannot imagine what thoſe People aile who murmur and complain in ſuch a ſtate, unleſs they be ſurfeited and ſick of Eaſe and Peace and Plenty. We have a <hi>Church</hi> whoſe Doctrine, Diſcipline and Government, is Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical and Primitive; defective in nothing ſo much as the Obedience of her Members, unleſs it be the Exerciſe of her Diſcipline; The hatred and terror of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Party, becauſe they know whereon we bottom, having preſcription from the pureſt Ages againſt all their intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Innovations</hi> and <hi>Corruptions,</hi> maintaining <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency</hi> according to the firſt Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, and moſt <hi>earneſtly contending for that Faith which was once delivered to the Saints;</hi> And if we be malign'd both by them and others for adhering moſt firmly to the Government, it ought to be our joy, it is our glory; For <hi>this Church</hi> was always famous for her <hi>untainted</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Loyalty to the Crown. Oh that our <hi>Lives</hi> were as good as our <hi>Religion,</hi> that our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation were ſuch as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, in Purity and Peaceableneſs, in Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Meekneſs, in Brotherly Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and that we were all united in conſulting our Intereſt as well as Duty, by a dutiful Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51325:18"/> to the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Laws:</hi> For believe me, among all the Propoſals which the various fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of private men can project, you will find this above all, <hi>The trueſt Expedient for Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion:</hi> where men cannot agree the Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides the difference, let us therefore agree at leaſt in This, <hi>To be decided by the Laws.</hi> And if our <hi>Diviſions</hi> ariſe chiefly from mens breaking the Laws, then it naturally follows, and the conſequence is ſo plain, that it needs no proof, the beſt way to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite</hi> us all is <hi>To keep the Laws. Brethren,</hi> keep your Laws, and your Laws under God will keep your Liberties, Properties and Religion ſafe. And more particularly I beſeech you, For the ſake of God and his Church, the Kings and your own, That you would all as becomes good Subjects give a ſpecial Inſtance of this Duty, while you tranſact the buſineſs of this day, That ſo <hi>God may be glorified, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtrengthened,</hi> and <hi>the City credited.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>PAg. 13. lin. 3. for <hi>arrear,</hi> read <hi>errour.</hi> Pag. 18. lin. 22. after <hi>God,</hi> add <hi>He calls him twice in one verſe the Miniſter of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
